Guide to the Carl W. Schmidt Jr. Photographs circa 1930s–1940s PR 275
New-York Historical Society
Carl W. Schmidt Jr. photographs
circa 1930s–1940s
New-York Historical Society
Schmidt, Carl W., Jr., 1916-1996
PR 275
0.71 Linear feet in 1 box (123 photoprints: gelatin silver; 7 x 10 inches or smaller).
Photographs taken throughout New York State—in the Adirondacks, at Montauk, Jones Beach, and Roosevelt Field on Long Island—and in New York City, where the bulk of the collection centers on the construction and completed attractions of the 1939-1940 New York World's Fair. Includes views of George Washington's Mount Vernon, and a number of images of ships at sea.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers by appointment only. To schedule an appointment, contact the Print Room Librarian at printroom@nyhistory.org.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Claire Griswold and Tom Schmidt, 2008.
Arrangement
Photographs are grouped alphabetically by location.
Biographical note
Carl W. Schmidt Jr. was born in Brooklyn, New York in 1916. He enlisted in the Coast Guard in 1936 and served until 1957. After retiring from the Coast Guard he moved to St. Petersburg, Florida, where he lived with his wife Rita and their seven children. In Florida Schmidt worked as a carpenter into his sixties. Along with photography, he had passions for model trains and planes, which are evident in his photographs. Schmidt died in Florida in 1996.
Scope and Contents
The Carl W. Schmidt Jr. Photographs span from the 1930s through the 1940s. The collection contains snapshots primarily of transportation, planes, trains, and ships, as well as photographs of the 1939 World's Fair. The collection contains 123 gelatin silver prints ranging in size from 2 3/4 x 4 inches to 7 x 10 inches.
Photographs of New York State include images of St. Regis Mountain and Whiteface Mountain, part of the Adirondack Mountains. Long Island images include the Jones Beach water tower and East Bathhouse, and Montauk Point beach and lighthouse. A large number of Long Island photographs were taken at Roosevelt Field and feature a variety of airplanes at the airfield. Manhattan images show the city viewed from the Empire State Building as well as an image of the Empire State building from the street. One image of Jamaica, Queens shows a snow-covered house. Mount Vernon images show George Washington's home and burial site.
The bulk of the images in this collection were taken at the 1939 World's Fair. Two photographs show the location as construction of the fair site had just begun. Included in general views of the fair is a small panorama, made from three photographs, showing the entire fair site. Other photos show many of the pavilions, the Trylon and Perisphere, and several night views. Also included are many of the railroad engines on display.
Unidentified locations contain mainly images of ships at sea. One particularly interesting image shows the U.S.S. Dirigible Akron moored to the U.S.S. Patoka. This folder also contains an image of an oil derrick.
Gelatin silver prints.; Photographic prints.; Airplanes -- Photographs; Locomotives -- Photographs; Transportation -- Photographs; Adirondack Mountains (N.Y.) -- Photographs.; Jamaica (New York, N.Y.) -- Photographs; Jones Beach State Park (N.Y.) -- Photographs; Montauk Point (N.Y.) -- Photographs; Mount Vernon (Va.: Estate) -- Photographs; New York (N.Y.) -- Photographs.; Floyd Bennett Field (New York, N.Y.) -- Photographs; New York World's Fair (1939-1940: New York, N.Y.) [111] -- Photographs; Roosevelt Field (Airport: Garden City, N.Y.) -- Photographs
- Photographic prints
  Scope and Contents
  123 prints, 7 x 10 inches or smaller.
  - New York State—Adirondack Mountains, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Includes St. Regis Mountain and Whiteface Mountain.
  - New York State—Long Island—Jones Beach, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Includes images of the Jones Beach water tower and East Bathhouse.
  - New York State—Long Island—Montauk Point, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Includes images of the beach and lighthouse.
  - New York State—Long Island—Roosevelt Field, 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Includes images of a variety of planes at the airfield.
  - New York City—Brooklyn—Floyd Bennett Field, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - New York City—Manhattan, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Includes views taken from the Empire State Building as well as an image of the Empire State Building from the street.
  - New York City—Queens—Flushing—World's Fair, construction, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - New York City—Queens—Flushing—World's Fair, general, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
    Includes a small panorama, made from three photographs, showing the entire fair site.
  - New York City—Queens—Flushing—World's Fair, railroads, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Includes shots of railroad engines on display at the fair.
  - New York City—Queens—Jamaica, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    General
    Includes one view of a snow-covered house.
  - Virginia—Mount Vernon, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 9 [12?])
    Images of George Washington's home and burial site.
  - Unidentified locations, [circa 1930s], undated (Box 1, Folder 10 [13?])
    Contains mainly images of ships at sea, one of which shows the U.S.S. Dirigible Akron moored to the U.S.S. Patoka. Another shows an oil derrick.